Adam Sedgwick Collection 1825-1870 Mss.B.Se25L
American Philosophical Society
Such were the geologic theories at the time Sedgwick was doing his most important field work. In the field, Sedgwick had a flair for grasping the regional significance of local details, developing ideas on stratigraphical continuity that effectively showed links between formations. Among the important field work he did was to explain the nature of the New Red Sandstone (a term no longer used) by using the distinctive Magnesia Limestone of northeastern England and them to correlate the Sandstone with classic successions in Germany. In his "Remarks on the Structure of Large Mineral Masses" (1835) Sedgwick used his mathematical training along with his skill in the field to clearly analyze the effects of diagenesis; in the same paper he provided the crucial technical key to interpreting complex folding by distinctively explaining stratification, jointing, and cleavage. Also, in collaboration with Robert Impey Murchison (1792-1871), Sedgwick discovered that some rocks in Devonshire were lateral equivalents of the well-known Old Red Sandstone and in so doing named a new geologic period: Devonian.
A long and often bitter controversy with Murchison was a significant feature of Sedgwick's career. Both men desired to be the discoverer of the strata where the first fossils were to be found. Sedgwick's Cambrian System, which he was first to define, was very thick, and its upper reaches contained fossils of invertebrate fauna. The fossil record seemed to begin in the Cambrian. Murchison began to assert, however, that the Upper Cambrian was in reality part of "his" Silurian System of younger rock; he eventually added almost all of the fossiliferous Cambrian to the Silurian System. The dispute was aggravated by what Sedgwick viewed as editorial tampering by the Geological Society with one of his papers. In a display of temper (Sedgwick's least attractive characteristic) Sedgwick broke off ties with the Society.
Sedgwick eventually discovered that Murchison had confused strata in two places, which in one instance created a spurious uniformity in Silurian fossils. Murchison, however, would not admit his errors, so the two men remained estranged. Later, other geologists discovered more fossils that were defined as Cambrian and added a geologic age with representative fossils named the Ordovician that comprised Sedgwick's Upper Cambrian and Murchison's Lower Silurian.
Sedgwick's most famous student was Charles Darwin, who accompanied Sedgwick on a trip to Wales. The lessons in practical geology provided great dividends when Darwin put them to work during his Beagle voyage. Sedgwick also furthered Darwin's career by reading some of his work to the Geological Society. However, Sedgwick did not believe in the transmutation of species as laid out in Darwin's Origin of Species.
The root of Sedgwick's opposition was that in removing God from the origin of flora and fauna, and thus removing intelligent design from the natural world, human moral responsibility is undermined. The universe is governed by an active intelligence, present in the design and purpose observable in the natural world of mutual dependence. The world is old, as the geologic evidence shows, but that does not preclude species coming and going over time due to catastrophes originating from the Creator, a force beyond human comprehension. Contemplating nature leads one closer to the mind God. Sedgwick was far from a fundamentalist. He attacked simple Mosaic interpretations of natural history, but he also believed that materialists ignored evidence of design.
Despite all the controversies, and despite being viewed late in his long life as a superannuated figure, Sedgwick was widely admired as a warmhearted and noble person. His contributions to geology were recognized with the award of the Wollaston Medal from the Geological Society in 1833 and the Copley Medal from the Royal Society in 1863. His greatest legacy might be his role in developing university science education. He died in 1873.
Airy, George Biddell, Sir, 1801-1892; Clift, William, 1775-1849; De La Beche, Henry T., (Henry Thomas), 1796-1855; Geological Society of London; James, John. K., Sir, bart., 1815-1893; Lloyd, Humphrey, 1800-1881; Lonsdale, W. (William), 1794-1871; Palmerston, Henry John Temple, Viscount, 1784-1865; Peacock, George, 1791-1858; Procter, Joseph, b. 1829; Sedgwick Museum; Sopwith, Thomas, 1803-1879; University of Cambridge.; Beyond Early America; Geology--Great Britain; Geology--Study and teaching (Higher); Religion; Scientific Correspondence; Sedbergh (England)
- Correspondence, 1825-1870; 0.25 lin. feet (Box 1)
  - ALS to Joseph Procter, [1825] Dec. 29; 1p.
    Scope and Contents note
    Looking forward to seeing him especially if he brings a "plumper for Palmerston" [for election as burgess of Cambridge University]. Remembers [Thomas] Musgrave to Procter. Written from "Lord Palmerston's Committee Room."
    Immediate Source of Acquisition note
    1981 1963ms
  - ALS to W. Clift, 1827 May 22; 1p.
    Asking Clift to help Rev. Charles Joseph in seeing the Hunterian Museum at the Royal College of Surgeons. Notes bought the elk horns of "Sowerby"
    removed from B: AL1.3
  - ALS to My dear Sir, [1829] Nov. 13; 4p.
    Encloses a note [missing] for Mr. Woodward who would give the correspondent "the information you want"; mentions Sowerby and Museum cabinets; Mr. Latter is coming to Cambridge this week; asks about mineral specimens; "Mr. Tennant succeeded Mawe" in the Strand mineral shop; correspondent has a son who would be a sizar; AS gives information on becoming a sizar and scholar
    1983 780ms
  - ALS to My dear Sir, 1831 July 7; 2p.
    Asks correspondent to notify Mr. Airy that a friend of AS's named West(?) is coming north to assist Airy on his walk in the Highlands and Cape Wrath
    1974 1450ms
  - ALS to Dear Sir, [After 1831]; 2p.
    Asks that 3 copies of his anniversary addresses to the Geological Society in 1830 and 1831 be bound with other addresses
    1979 1661ms
  - ALS to H. Lloyd, [1832] February 25; 4p.
    Lloyd sent parcel with copies of "Dublin problems" (mathematical questions); Sedgwick has been ill; bulk of letter explains history of the use of the "Royal Privilege" by the Crown in using the mandamus petition to grant divinity degrees; mentions that [Samuel?] Lee might have gotten one to qualify for the "Arabic" professorship; advice on Irish Geological Museum
    1971 1189ms
  - ALS to My dear Sir, 1840 July 2; 3p.
    Taking waters, "driving off rheumatic gout and stimulating a sluggish liver"; Going to Norwich to his Residence (prebendary); will miss meeting in Glasgow; mentions Geological Museum, then being built
  - ALS to My dear Sir, [1842] Jan. 13; 1p.
    Son of the late Mr. Bowman has sent a box of Bala fossils to correspondent, who has seen the ones AS and Murchison collected in 1834; might contain new species Mr Bowman collected; AS wants to compare with Coniston Water Head; AS now believes Bala on lower parallel than Coniston; Snowdons lie "many thousand feet lower still, but the old species" still show; earlier sent correspondent box of upper greywacke fossils
    1967 2641ms
  - ALS to My dear Lonsdale, [1842] Apr. 12; 2p.
    Asks [William] Lonsdale to forward the note to Mr. [Thomas] Sopwith who is likely in Newcastle [Thomas' hometown] asking Sopwith to come to Cambridge this week and then they can go to meeting of Geological Society together; AS has audit and then inspection of his new museum which moved into new quarters last year; he intends to ask [James de Carle?] Sowerby to help with exhibit
  - ALS My dear Sir, 1842 Apr. 26; 3p.
    Museum advancing; suffering from "suppressed gout" that AS wishes would "show its face at the surface instead of lurking among my vitals, & poisoning the fresh air of life"; wants correspondent to make a "model" for his fall lectures, similar to the one of the Forest of Dean he saw at De la Beche's, which AS could cover and use as a table; mentions how the real Forest would "cure" him
  - ALS to My dear Sir, 1842 May 1; 3p.
    Detailed instructions on what is needed to set up a model for his lectures, mounted like the one at the Economical Club, where De la Beche's model is; model is to have a "stout cover capable of being locked down for I should not wish it to be exposed to public view without permission"; is on a "severe diet" to "mitigate my malady"
    974 1450ms
  - ALS to My dear Sir, 1842 October 25; 2p.
    No hurry on model since will need it only when AS gets back to Cambridge at Christmas; can't give correspondent directions about the "Old Red" [sandstone] which in "that country" (Forest of Dean?) with the middle part containing limestone and the lower part slate; has severe cold, worse since influenza in Jan. 1837
  - ALS to My dear Sir, 1842 Nov. 3; 2p.
    Correspondent sent a parcel to Norwich; OK for correspondent to use the model until AS needs it in Jan.; AS's cold is better but still confined to house; was not at Norwich for the festival
  - ALS to My dear Sir, 1843 Jan. 30; 2p.
    Has arranged credit or 56 pounds for the correspondent with Jonathan(?) Lambert & Co.; AS saw a blast that brought down some chalk cliffs at Dover and saw John Herschel and Professor Airy there; model is on its legs and is all he could wish
    (1974 1450ms)
  - ALS to My dear Sir, [1844 (Sept.?)]; 3p.
    Thanks correspondent for two pamphlets, one on the mustard tree and one on the history of Scriptures; is feeling gouty; Wiesbaden cure did no good even after two months
  - ALS to Miller, 1846 Oct. 11; 4p.
    Asks [Hugh?} Miller about a book on behalf of "Mrs. Williams" maybe called the Cambrian Lyre that is supposedly translated from the Celtic. Anecdote about going to visit Wales, asking a Welsh lad where "Mr. Williams" is, the lad not understanding until AS said "Dr. Williams." Correspondent friends with the Williamses who apparently live in Llandovery.
    1976 1490.fms
  - ALS to Dear Sir, 1847 March 1; 4p.
    Explains activities that have prevented him from writing sooner, including a recent election; AS on winning side. Pleased to respond to grandson of Mr. Foster of Hebblethwaite Hall in Sedbergh. Reminesces about Mr. Foster, of "uncommon stamp." Last saw him in Newcastle, visiting a cut glass factory. When last in Sedbergh, all the people AS knew seemed to be gone
    1971 1667ms
  - ALS to My dear Peacock, 1847 March; 2p.
    Meant to forward "Lord Monteagle's hieroglyphics" to Peacock and would like to go with the letter himself but he has a cold; unity of Trinity College a problem; AS did his "utmost to keep good humour" around him during the recent election of Prince Albert to the Chancellorship of Cambridge; Monteagle in his letter says that the Prince accepts the office; AS had "two or three bleedings" to clear his "stuffed and loaded" head
    1975 92ms
  - ALS to My dear Sir, 1848; 3p.
    AS made some unspecified "stupid blunder"; requests correspondent to return with AS from London, where he is undertaking a work of "inspection"; AS can give correspondent two or three clear days; AS hadn't heard that Henry Thomas De la Beche was to be knighted, but "I hope now that he mounts his spurs he will not drop his hammer"
  - ALS to My Sir, 1849 Feb. 2; 1p.
    Thanks correspondent [Rev. C. B. Smyth] for sending his book The Sicilian Vespers; will become a subscriber; AS intends to work on book on Christian Metaphysics
    1972 434ms
  - ALS to unidentified, 1850 Aug. 14; 2p.
    Knows the College spit ceases to turn without Professor Sedgwick, but the Duchess of Argyll has given him an invitation, and it is Sedgwick's policy that whenever "duty & inclination have a fight, he thinks it best & most manly that inclination should win"; it is a "severe code of morals for a poor old Monk" but he will ask for the Duchess' "grace and absolution" tomorrow
    B Se25L
  - ALS to My dear Sir, 1850 Dec. 5; 2p.
    Ill, but wants to attend audit of Norwich Chapter and go to Trinity College for its audit. Is worried about it. Is delivering lecture to the Geological Society. Wishes correspondent luck with his Literary Gazette [likely correspondent is William Jerdan, editor of the Literary Gazette]
    1955 1030ms
  - ALS to My dear Sir, 1854 June 19; 3p.
    Apologizes for not writing sooner, lost the letter on his desk, will be back in Cambridge in July; wants to see antiquarian friends to "attend Hall" with them where Sedgwick is "Master & Lord of the Spit"; jokes that antiquarian friends forget to eat; admires archaeologist [Albert] Way; good news about the "Norwich window"
  - ALS to Sir James [Sir John Kingston James], 1855 Dec. 18; 3p.
    Declines invitation to a Bachelor Ball due to age and ill health. Wishes he "could take the load of the last 40 years off my sholders." Can't join the "sect of jumpers"; we all must join in the "dance of Death."
    1979 1519ms
  - ALS to Fox Taylor or Richard Gerrain(?), 1856 March 22; 2p.
    Letter written on a printed circular with four letters by Sedgwick from Cambridge Papers Feb. 23, 1856, concerning the purchase of a paleontology collection of Rev. T. Image for 250 pounds plus 100 pounds for exhibiting it. "Gout drives me out of bed & almost to mania"; Circular intended for MA's; is seeking more subscriptions; has fallen short; correspondent is "brother geologist"; the Residents at Cambridge have been generous
    1984 196ms
  - ALS to My dear Lady Affleck, [1858-1865] June 19; 1p.
    Accepts an invitation to dinner [Lady Affleck (d. 1865) was wife of William Whewell, who married her in 1858]
    1980 1301ms
  - ALS to C. B. [Charles Bagot] Caley, [1860] Feb. 27; 1p.
    While normally doesn't do so, agrees in this case to subscribe to Cayley's work "Metrical Version of the Psalms"; [came out as The Psalms in Metre, London: Longman, Green, Longman, and Roberts, 1860]
  - ALS to Mr. Atkinson, [1862?] Dec. 24; 4p.
    Son and wife and grandson Adam arrived unexpectedly by train after a "wild, cold, uncertain drive" to Langcliff; asks if he could visit Mr. Atkinson; will be there for "xtmas"; other personal circumstances noted
  - ALS ALS to Mr. Atkinson, 1863 22 June; 4p.
    Talks of weather, finally getting outside and "cast my skin, as some reptiles do" and got some sun; believes books of "Coleazo"(?) have problematic thinking; thanks Atkinson for a photograph; plans a party
    1971 1819ms
  - ALS to T. Bailey Lanyborn, 1864 July 30; 1p.
    Thanks for searching for Cowgill's paper; mentions the bad state of "the late Mr. Burder's (?) papers"
    1972 476ms
  - ALS to Mrs. Webb, 1864 Sept. 17; 4p.
    Thanks for letter, reminisces about correspondent's father and mother when AS first went to Norwich; AS ordained with her father; late friend from Cambridge student days [Joseph] Romilly mentioned; talks of old age; has family guests; nephew had attack of "monomania" early 1863
  - ALS to My dear Lord, 1867 Jan. 5; 4p.
    Correspondent should have received AS's "Memorial for the Trustees for Cowgill Chapel"; history of the Chapel; urges correspondent to read especially particular parts of the "Memorial"
  - ALS to My dear Sir, 1867 Aug. 26; 2p.
    Correspondent bought a photograph of AS; latest illness; leaves for Cambridge end of Sept.
  - ALS to My dear Adam, 1870 April 11; 4p.
    To meet correspondent in Bath at the York House Hotel, take baths, go to Salisbury, then go to Dent [AS went to Bath with his great nephew Adam Sedgwick]
  - LS to Dear Sir, 1870 Nov. 27; 4p.
    Thanks for two pamphlets of the Report of the Proceedings of the Cotteswold Club and a copy of correspondent's essay on the "Charnwood Gravels"; field work has long ended and reading days may be over; bothered by bronchitis but hopes to get through last lectures
    1955 1031ms
  - ALS to Mr. Charlesworth, 1870 Dec. 12; 3p.
    AS withdrawals his signature from a paper given him by Charlesworth because it was not in regular printer's form and AS does not know the person or his work
  - ALS to My dear Sir, Apr. 11; 1p.
    Tries to reach correspondent to say impossible to meet correspondent in London this week - had thought meeting of Geological Society was this week but is next week Wed.; would be convenient to rendezvous in Cambridge and go to London together; apologizes for mistake and partly blames sickness
  - ALS to unidentified, Monday morning; 1p.
    Asks correspondent to have wine with him.
    removed from call number B:AL1.2